Finding Aid for John B. Swainson Papers 1943-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Gubernatorial Career (1961-1963) 1960-1963
  - Press Office
    - Sound Recordings
      - November 2, 1961 Mental Health Conference, Kalamazoo, Michigan, 3 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes; 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 50)
      - January 15, 1962 JBS interview with Lou Gordon, 1 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes; 7 1/2 ips; 5 in. (Box 50)
      - April 7, 1962 Speeches of Lynn Bartlett and Philip A. Hart, 1 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes; 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 50)
      - May 5, 1962 JBS speaking at Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner, 1 audiotapes 7 1/2 ips; 7 in.; reel-to-reel tapes 30 minutes (Box 50)
      - June 13, 1962 WBRB (Macomb County) phone-in radio program, "Sound Off" with JBS discussing politics and public issues, 2 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes; 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Box 50)
      - September 15, 1962 JBS speaking at Mount Pleasant High School, 1 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes; 3 3/4 ips; 7 in (Box 50)
      - September 24, 1962 JBS at NAACP dinner, Detroit, Michigan, 1 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes; 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 50)
      - 1962 undated Campaign song, "Governor John" sung by University of Detroit students, 1 audiotapes 3 minutes 7 1/2 ips; 7 in.; reel-to-reel tapes (Box 50)
  - Proclamations 1961-1962
    - A-E (Box 51)
    - F-O (Box 52)
    - P-Z (Box 53)
  - Study Commissions, Advisory Committees, etc
    - General (Box 54)
    - Agriculture, Advisory Committee on 1962 (Box 54)
    - Annexation Legislation Advisory Committee 1962 (Box 54)
    - Anti-Litter Study Committee 1962, 3 folders (Box 54)
    - Atomic Energy Study Commission, Governor's 1961-1962, 3 folders (Box 54)
    - Audit Procedures, Collections and Disbursements, Committee on 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 54)
    - Children and Youth, Inter-departmental Staff on 1960-1961 (Box 54)
    - Cultural Commission, Michigan 1961-1962
      - General, 2 folders (Box 54)
      - Indecent literature (Box 54)
    - Displaced Persons and Refugees (Study Commission) (Box 54)
    - Economic Future, Committee on Michigan's 1960-1962, 3 folders (Box 54)
    - Emergency Planning, Michigan Office of (Box 54)
    - Employment of the Physically Handicapped, Governor's Commission on 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Fair Campaign Practices Committee 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Fair Grounds Development Commission 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Foreign Trade Expansion Commission 1962 (Box 55)
    - Health Care, Governor's Advisory Commission on, 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Indian Problems, Governor's Study Commission on Michigan 1961 (Box 55)
    - Independent Schools, Committee on the Study of 1962 (Box 55)
    - Industrial Development Legislation Commission 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Industrial Safety Commission and Advisory Council 1961 (Box 55)
    - Indepartmental Resource Development Committee 1962 (Box 55)
    - Labor Mediation, Advisory Council 1961 (Box 55)
    - Manpower Development Committee 1962, 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Mental Health and Education, Governor's Conferences on 1961 (Box 55)
    - Mental Retardation Committee, Governor's 1962 (Box 55)
    - Personnel Council Practices, Temporary Committee on 1960 (Box 55)
    - Prepaid Hospital and Medical Care Plans, Governor's Study Commission on 1960-1962, 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Recreation Study Commission 1960 (Box 55)
    - Reorganization of State Government, Advisory Committee on 1960-1962, 3 folders (Box 56)
    - Science, Industry and Education, Council of Consultants on 1961 (Box 56)
    - Senate Apportionment, Governor's Committee on 1962 (Box 56)
    - Sesquicentennial Commission 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 56)
    - Ski Lift Safety Study Commission 1962 (Box 56)
    - Small Business Study Commission 1961 (Box 56)
    - Status of Women, Governor's Commission on 1962, 2 folders (Box 56)
    - Workmen's Compensation Study Commission 1962 (Box 56)
    - Youth (Michigan Youth Commission) 1961-1962, 4 folders (Box 56)
  - Governors' Conferences 1961-1962
    - Conference folders (Box 57)
  - Gubernatorial appointments
    - Biographical files (Box 58)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 58)
    - Boards and Commissions [A-C] (Box 59)
    - Boards and Commissions [C-M] (Box 60)
    - Boards and Commissions [M-Y] (Box 61)
    - State Courts (Box 62)
    - State Courts (Box 63)
    - Federal Appointments (Box 63)
  - Staff files
    - Richard Miller, Legislative Secretary
      - Agency/Department bill analyses
        - Administration, Department of, 4 folders (Box 64)
        - Aeronautics (Box 64)
        - Agriculture (Box 64)
        - Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Michigan State Board of Registration for (Box 64)
        - Attorney General (Box 64)
        - Auditor General (Box 64)
        - Banking (Box 64)
        - Barbers (Box 64)
        - Blind, Michigan School for the (Box 64)
        - Chiropody (Box 64)
        - Civil Defense Office (Box 64)
        - Civil Service Commission (Box 64)
        - Conservation (Box 64)
        - Corporation and Securities Commission (Box 64)
        - Corrections (Box 64)
        - Crippled Children Commission (Box 64)
        - Dentistry (Box 64)
        - Eastern Michigan University (Box 64)
        - Economic Development Commission (Box 64)
        - Education, State Board of (Box 64)
        - Electrical Administrative Board (Box 64)
        - Employment Security Commission (Box 64)
        - Fair Employment Practices Commission (Box 64)
        - Fair, Michigan State (Box 64)
        - Fair, Upper Peninsula State (Box 64)
        - Foresters, Board of Registration (Box 64)
        - Health Department (Box 64)
        - Highway Department (Box 64)
        - Historical Commission (Box 64)
        - Insurance Department (Box 64)
        - Inter-agency Council for Recreation (Box 64)
        - Interstate Cooperation, Commission on (Box 64)
        - Labor Department (Box 64)
        - Labor Mediation Board (Box 64)
        - Law Examiners, State Board of (Box 64)
        - Library, Michigan State (Box 64)
        - Liquor Control Commission (Box 64)
        - Medicine, State Board of Registration in (Box 64)
        - Mental Health Department (Box 64)
        - Michigan College of Mining and Technology (Box 64)
        - Michigan State University (Box 64)
        - Military Establishment (Box 64)
        - Mortuary Science Board (Box 64)
        - Northern Michigan University (Box 64)
        - Optometry, State Board of Examiners in (Box 64)
        - Osteopathic Registration and Examination, Board of (Box 64)
        - Pharmacy (Box 64)
        - Plumbing Board (Box 64)
        - Police, State (Box 64)
        - Public Instruction (Box 64)
        - Public Service Commission (Box 64)
        - Racing Commission (Box 64)
        - Retirement-Employees (Box 64)
        - Retirement-School Employees (Box 64)
        - Revenue Department (Box 64)
        - Safety Commission (Box 64)
        - Secretary of State (Box 65)
        - Social Welfare Commission (Box 65)
        - Tax Commission (Box 65)
        - Tourist Council (Box 65)
        - Treasurer, State (Box 65)
        - University of Michigan (Box 65)
        - Water Resources Commission (Box 65)
        - Wayne State University (Box 65)
        - Workmen's Compensation Commission (Box 65)
      - Legislative background files [A-Z]
        - Aged, Medical Care for the (Box 65)
        - Aging Commission (Box 65)
        - Agriculture (Box 65)
        - Appropriations, 2 folders (Box 65)
        - Atomic Energy (Box 65)
        - Budget (Box 65)
        - Civil Defense (Box 65)
        - Congressional (Box 65)
        - Constitutional Convention (Box 65)
        - Education, Public School (Box 65)
        - Housing and Home Finance Agency (Box 65)
        - Howell Sanatorium (Box 65)
        - Legislative meetings, 4 folders (Box 65)
        - Mackinac Bridge (Box 65)
        - Reapportionment (Box 65)
        - Recreation (Box 65)
        - Sleeping Bear Dunes (Box 65)
        - Taxation (Box 65)
        - Tourist Council (Box 65)
        - Unemployment Compensation (Box 65)
        - Youth (Box 65)
        - Youth Commission (Box 65)
        - Youth Opportunities Program (Box 65)
      - Legislative Program for 1961
        - Age (Box 65)
        - Consumer Protection (Box 65)
        - Economic Growth (Box 65)
        - Education (Box 65)
        - Employment (Box 65)
        - Fiscal Policy (Box 65)
        - Human Rights (Box 65)
        - Local Government (Box 65)
        - Mental Health-Western Central Michigan Hospital (Box 65)
        - State Government Reorganization (Box 65)
      - Legislative Program for 1962, 1 folders; 1 volumes (Box 65)
      - Legislative Program for 1963
        - Agency recommendations, 3 folders (Box 66)
        - Legislative program
          - General (Box 66)
          - Agriculture (Box 66)
          - Apportionment (Box 66)
          - Budget (Box 66)
          - Civil Rights (Box 66)
          - Economic Development (Box 66)
          - Greater Michigan Authority (Box 66)
          - Higher Education (Box 66)
          - Primary and Secondary Education (Box 66)
          - Youth (Box 66)
      - Michigan Democratic Party activities 1962-1965 (post-Swainson administration) (Box 66)
        (Miller was Special Assistant for Legislative Affairs of the Michigan Democratic Party)
    - Lattie Coor, Administrative Assistant
      - Topical files (Box 67)
    - Doris Jarrell, Administrative Assistant
      - Topical files (Box 67)
        (Doris Jarrell was appointed administrative assistant in October 1961. Her responsibilities were in the area of research and to assist the governor's news secretary Thaddeus Ogar)
    - Jordan Popkin, Administrative Officer, files
      (Jordan Popkin resigned as administrative assistant October 1961)
      - Children and Youth (Box 67)
      - Mental Health (Box 67)
      - Social Welfare (Box 67)
    - Robert A. Derengoski, Legal Advisor, files
      - Commutations (Box 67)
      - Extraditions (Box 67)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Department of Administration (Ira Polley, controller), memoranda (Box 68)
    - August 1960-December 1962, 12 folders (Box 68)
    - Post-campaign correspondence, 9 folders (Box 68)
    - Report to Governor-Elect Romney of special advisory study commissions December 28, 1962 (Box 68)
    - December 1962 (end of administration) correspondence, 2 folders (Box 68)
    - 1962 Campaign
      - Campaign Headquarters
        - Correspondence (Box 69)
        - Public Relations (Box 69)
        - Reports (Box 69)
      - Campaign Publications and Materials (Box 69)
      - Farnum, Billie (Box 69)
      - Speeches (Box 69)
      - State Democratic Committee (Box 69)
      - Swainson-Romney Debate (Box 69)
      - Topical Reports
        - Agriculture (Box 69)
        - Area Redevelopment Administration (Box 69)
        - Banks (Box 69)
        - Civil Defense (Box 69)
        - Civil Rights (Box 69)
        - Conservation and Recreation (Box 69)
        - Consumer Protection (Box 69)
        - Corrections System (Box 69)
        - Economic Development (Box 69)
        - Economy in Government (Box 69)
        - Education (Box 69)
        - Employment (Box 69)
        - Government Regulation (Box 69)
        - Health (Box 69)
        - Highway (Box 69)
        - Insurance (Box 69)
        - Manpower Development and Training (Box 69)
        - Mental Health (Box 69)
        - Municipal Finance (Box 69)
        - Revenue and Taxes (Box 69)
        - Senior Citizens (Box 69)
        - Social Welfare (Box 69)
        - Tourist Council (Box 69)
        - Water Resources (Box 69)
        - Waterways (Box 69)
        - Youth (Box 69)
      - Voelker, John (Box 69)
    - Governor's Office
      - Apportionment (Box 69)
      - Governor's Inauguration 1/1/1961 (Box 69)
      - Personal Correspondence 1961-1962 (Box 69)
      - Staff Memos
        - 1961 (Box 69)
        - 1962 (Box 69)
      - Trip to Washington DC January 19-20, 1962 (Box 69)
      - Unemployment Compensation (Box 69)
      - Year-end Meetings with Government Agencies, Boards and Commissions (Box 69)
    - John F. Kennedy's Inauguration (Box 69)
- Post-gubernatorial Career 1963-1975
  This Post-gubernatorial consists of a portion of those files created by Swainson after leaving the governor's office.
  - Miscellaneous
    - Correspondence 1963-1975, 16 folders (Box 70)
    - Clippings 1963-1965 (Box 70)
  - Topical files
    - Alpheus Felch Society 1973 (Box 70)
    - Detroit Olympic Committee 1962-1963 (Box 70)
    - Marine Hospital Treatment Center 1969-1970 (Box 70)
    - Mayor's Committee for Drug Rehabilitation 1970 (Box 70)
    - Michigan Association for Emotionally Disturbed Children 1967-1970, 2 folders (Box 70)
    - Michigan Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice 1969-1970 (Box 70)
    - Michigan Judges Association 1966-1969 (Box 70)
    - Miscellaneous 1963-1965 (Box 70)
    - Narcotics Addiction Rehabilitation Co-ordinating Organization (NARCO)
      - Board meetings 1969-1970 (Box 70)
      - Correspondence 1969-1970 (Box 70)
      - Ed Leibson 1969-1970 (Box 70)
      - Proposals 1970 (Box 70)
      - Miscellaneous 1969-1970 (Box 70)
    - Personal financial papers
      - Tax returns 1960-1974 (Box 71)
      - Tax return audit of 1967 (Box 71)
        (for 1962-1964 returns)
      - Miscellaneous financial papers (Box 71)
    - Sage Publications, "Right to Treatment" essay 1972 (Box 71)
    - Speeches 1963-1974, 2 folders (Box 71)
  - Family papers (Box 72)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials subgroup consists of photographs and motion picture films primarily during the period when Swainson was governor, but also including some photographs from his post-gubernatorial years.
  - Photographs
    - Public life (Box 73)
    - State Senator 1953-1959 (includes undated) (Box 73)
    - Lieutenant Governor Swainson 1959-1960, undated
      - General (Box 73)
      - Inauguration (Box 73)
      - Williams, G. Mennen (Box 73)
    - Governor 1961-1962, undated
      - Addresses (Box 73)
      - Administrative Board (Box 73)
      - Agriculture (State Fairs, 4-H Clubs, and Michigan Farmers Week) (Box 73)
      - Boy Scouts (Box 73)
      - Capitol, State (Box 73)
      - Ceremonies (Box 73)
      - Conferences, Conventions, Meetings, and Seminars (includes National Governors' Conference) (Box 73)
      - Consumers' Power Company (Big Rock Point Nuclear Plant, Charlevoix, Michigan) 1961 (Box 73)
      - Ecorse Water Festival 1962 (Box 73)
      - Education and educators (Box 73)
      - Groups
        - Identified (Box 73)
        - Unidentified (Box 73)
          (see also outsize photographs, Ac)
      - Honors and awards (personal and other) (Box 73)
      - Hungarian Freedom Fighters Federation (Box 73)
      - Inauguration (Box 73)
      - Industry
        - General (Box 73)
          (see also Consumers' Power Company)
        - Awards (Box 73)
      - Japanese Governors Visit 1962 (Box 73)
      - Judges (Box 73)
      - Labor (Box 73)
        includes photos of Walter Reuther and August Scholle
      - Mackinac Bridge (Box 73)
      - Manpower Development Act (mostly photos of bill signings) (Box 73)
      - Medical Care (includes photos of Swainson with handicapped persons) (Box 73)
      - Military
        - General (Box 73)
          (includes speeches, awards, and troop reviews)
          (see also outsize photographs)
        - Adjutant General of Michigan (Ronald D. McDonald) (Box 73)
        - Armed Forces Day 1961-1962 (Box 73)
        - Visiting Commanders May 1961 (Box 73)
      - Office Shots
        - Identified (Box 73)
        - Unidentified (Box 73)
      - Political
        - Campaigns (Box 73)
          (includes 1960 and1962 campaigns for Governor)
        - Cavanagh, Jerome (Box 73)
        - Democratic Convention 1960 (state) (Box 73)
        - Democratic Party (Box 73)
        - Hart, Philip A. (Box 73)
        - Humphrey, Hubert (Box 73)
        - Johnson, Lyndon B (Box 73)
        - Kelley, Frank (Box 73)
        - Kennedy, John F. (Box 73)
          (most appear to be from the 1960 and 1962 campaigns)
        - Public figures-Michigan
          - Signed portraits (Box 73)
          - Unsigned portraits (Box 73)
        - Public figures-United States
          - General (Box 73)
          - Signed (Box 73)
      - Sports and sports figures (Box 73)
        (mostly of Old Timers Football Camp, Michigan State University, 1962)
      - Staff (Box 73)
      - Swearing-in of Officials (Box 73)
      - Television appearance, probably 1961 (Box 73)
      - World's Fair, Seattle, Michigan Day 1962 (Box 73)
    - Post-gubernatorial
      - Democratic party: state and national (Box 73)
        (includes photos of JBS with Jimmy Carter, Lyndon Johnson, Edmund Muskie, Larry O'Brien, August Scholle, and G. Mennen Williams)
      - Honorary Degree, Grand Valley College 1972 (Box 73)
      - Judicial
        (includes photos of members of the Michigan Supreme Court)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 73)
    - Personal Life (Box 73)
    - Captions for slides not received (Box 73)
    - Childhood (through high school) (Box 73)
    - College (Box 73)
    - Family
      - General (Box 73)
      - Parents (Box 73)
      - Swainson, Alice (Box 73)
    - Homes (Box 73)
    - Military Service (Box 73)
    - Outdoor activities (Box 73)
    - Portraits
      - Formal (Box 73)
      - Informal (Box 73)
  - Films, 16 mm, black and white
    - "Aid to Dependent Children of Unemployed Parents," February 13, 1962 (Box 73)
    - "Boat Safety, Boards and Commissions," 1962 (Box 73)
    - "Excerpts from State of the State message, January 11, 1962" January 11, 1962 (Box 73)
      (from station WWJ-TV, Detroit)
    - "Governor Swainson, Senators Hart and McNamara, Washington, D.C." Undated (Box 73)
    - "Governor Swainson speech" Undated (Box 73)
    - "Legislature's Action on Pay Raise," July 19, 1962 (Box 73)
    - "Put Youth on a Job," February 26, 1962 (Box 73)
    - "Steps to Implement the New Federal Manpower Retrain[ing] Act in Michigan," March 21, 1962 (Box 73)
    - "Tax Comment," 1961 (Box 73)
      (from newscast on station WWJ-TV, Detroit)
  - Drawings and cartoons
    - Gubernatorial campaigns (Folder 1)
    - "Time and 1/2" by Frank Williams 1960 (Folder 1)
      (Time magazine cover stressing Swainson's ties to labor)
    - "'62 Compact Model" by Art Poinier, Detroit News 1962 (Folder 1)
      (March 19? newspaper cartoon with George Romney riding in a jalopy)
    - State Legislature (Folder 1)
    - "Big Decision" by Frank Williams 1962 (Folder 1)
      (July 24? newspaper cartoon with GOP elephant worrying about the effects of reapportionment)
    - "For You, and You, and Especially You" no author undated (Folder 1)
      (Swainson vetoing GOP legislation)
    - "The Fugitive" by Frank Williams 1962 (Folder 1)
      (March 9, lack of fiscal responsibility)
    - "Show-off!" by Frank Williams February 3, 1961 (Folder 1)
      (JBS throwing rope to business while legislature watches)
    - "That's Easy" by Frank Williams January 27, 1960 (Folder 1)
      (a divided GOP state legislature delegation: liberals versus conservatives)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 1)
    - "Big Reds are Everywhere" by Scott M. undated (Folder 1)
      (Swainson in marching band uniform)
    - "I'm an Honorary Indian" by Frank Williams 1971 (Folder 1)
    - "Let's Not Be Hasty... He Deserves an Elevator!" by Art Poinier November 3, 1960 (Folder 1)
      (re: state economic problems)